Okay בוקר טוב, Boker tov, today's דף Daf is מ"ה, Mem Hey,
מנחות Menachos 45, we pick up with the משנה Mishna on the
bottom of מ"ד עמוד ב', Mem Dalet Amud Bet, we are back,
we're done with the world of תפילין, Tefillin, ספר תורה, Sefer Torah,
מזוזה, Mezuzah, ציצית, Tzitzis, we're back to the world of קרבנות, Korbanot,
but we're in a section about מעכבין זה את זה me'akvin zeh
et zeh or אין מעכבין זה את זה, ein me'akvin zeh et
zeh, when two things come together, does the absence of one prevent
the validity of the other? And to some degree, this is still
within the world of מנחות, Menachos, the previous משנה Mishna talked about
מנחת נסכים, Minchas Nesachim, about the flour and oil and the wine
that come with קרבנות, Korbanot, and here we're going to be talking
about various animals of the מוספים, Musafim, but מנחות Minchos will also
rear their head here. So let's take a look at the משנה.
Mishna. הפרים והאילים והכבשים אין מעכבין זה את זה, Hapirim veha'eilim vehakevasim
ein me'akvin zeh et zeh, cows and rams and sheep do not
hold back one another. So if you're, presumably this is talking about
a מוסף, Musaf, where a מוסף Musaf consists of a mix of
all those animals, and if you have some of the animals and
not all, you still bring the ones that you have, and it's
not just that if you don't have rams you still bring cows
as the גמרא Gemara will explain, even if you don't have all
the cows you still bring the cows that you do have. Well,
actually that'll become clear at the end of the משנה Mishna as
well. רבי שמעון אומר, Rabbi Shimon omer, Rabbi Shimon says, אם היו
להם פרים מרובים ולא היו להם נסכים, im hayu lahem parim merubim
velo hayu lahem nesachim, if they had enough money or, you know,
for to buy all the cows, you know, let's say you need,
you know, 14 cows on סוכות Sukkot or whatever, let's say, you
know, they had the money to buy all the cows, but if
they would use all that money, they wouldn't be able to bring
the wine and the flour, the מנחת נסכים Minchas Nesachim and the
נסכים Nesachim that come with the קרבנות. Korbanot. So what should they
do? יביא פר אחד ונסכים yavvi par echad venesachim or נסכיה nesacheha
or נסכיו nesachav ולא יקריבו כולם בלא נסכים. velo yakrivu kulam belo
nesachim. He says better to have one animal, one of the cows
with the נסכים Nesachim rather than to have all of them without,
you know, and without any נסכים. Nesachim. So he really sees that
the נסכים Nesachim and the animal is like one full unit, and
when you're missing the נסכים, Nesachim, okay, you're יוצא, yotzei, but, you
know, it's really that animal was a grade B as it were.
So better to have one grade A on the one that you
bring and not bring the others than to bring all of them
and have all of them be considered grade B.
Okay, so let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. הני פרים
וכבשים דהיכא, Hanei parim uchevasim deheicha, which, when we're talking about cows
and rams and sheep, which קרבנות Korbanot are we talking about? Of
the מוסף, Musaf, clearly it's in a מוסף Musaf context. אילימא דחג,
Eilima dechag, if it is סוכות, Sukkot, כמשפט כמשפטם כתיב בהו, kemishpat
kemishpatam ketiv beihu, it says by them according to the law, כמשפט,
kemishpat, and that means that they're all required. So presumably סוכות Sukkot
is an exception to the rule, even though the משנה Mishna did
not spell it out, the גמרא Gemara understands because of that phrase
that it
is that all are required for סוכות. Sukkot. אלא דראש חודש ועצרת
דחומש הפקודים. Ela derosh chodesh ve'atzeret dechumash hapikudim. Okay, so we're talking
about the מוסף Musaf of ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh and שבועות Shavuot
on that are mentioned in במדבר. Bamidbar. במדבר, Bamidbar, we call it
במדבר Bamidbar because it's, you know, one of the first words, but
חומש הפקודים Chumash Hapikudim is what the גמרא Gemara calls it, which
literally is the book of numbers, which is the same as, you
know, the Christian name for the book. Okay, so it is ראש
חודש Rosh Chodesh and
שבועות, Shavuot, their מוסף Musaf that is in במדבר. Bamidbar. Now of
course the question is whatever happened to פסח? Pesach? Whatever happened to,
you know, to ראש השנה? Rosh Hashanah? So, you know, to יום
כיפור, Yom Kippur, or to שמיני עצרת? Shemini Atzeret? So תוספות Tosafot
so as we're going to see,
the גמרא Gemara wants this
phrase פרים, אילים, וכבשים, parim, eilim, and kevasim, the plural to be
true all within one מוסף. Musaf. That we're talking about a מוסף
Musaf that has multiple cows, multiple כבשים kevasim and multiple אילים.
eilim. So in all those other קרבנות Korbanot of, you know, there's
only one איל, ayil, so the גמרא Gemara is not mentioning those.
Okay, and also one cow. Okay, but but we are going to
mention ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh and שבועות. Shavuot. Now even in ראש
חודש Rosh Chodesh and שבועות Shavuot and תוספות Tosafot has a whole
other discussion about why פסח Pesach isn't being mentioned. But anyway, even
in ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh and שבועות, Shavuot,
those don't really fit the description I just said. So let's take
a look at the top of מ"ה עמוד א'. Mem Hey Amud
Aleph. So the גמרא Gemara says אילים דהיכא, eilim deheicha, where are
you getting multiple rams?
אי דהנהו, ei dehanhu, if it is, you know, the ones that
are written there itself in במדבר, Bamidbar, דאיל הוא, de'ayil hu, so
it is only one ram. then it is only one ram. So
what is written in במדבר? Bamidbar? So let's take a look. So
for ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh it says, ובראשי חדשיכם תקריבו עולה לה׳
פרים בני בקר שנים ואיל אחד כבשים בני שנה שבעה תמימים. U'v'roshei
chodsheichem takrivu olah l'Hashem parim b'nei vakar shnayim v'ayil echad kvasim b'nei
shana shiva tmimim. One ram. Similarly by שבועות, Shavuos, וביום הבכורים בהקריבכם
מנחה חדשה לה׳ בשבועותיכם מקרא קדש יהיה לכם כל מלאכת עבודה לא
תעשו והקרבתם עולה לריח ניחוח לה׳ פרים בני בקר שנים איל אחד
שבעה כבשים בני שנה. U'v'yom habikurim b'hakrivchem mincha chadasha l'Hashem b'shavuoseichem mikra
kodesh yihye lachem kol m'leches avoda lo sa'asu v'hikravtem olah l'reiach nichoach
l'Hashem parim b'nei vakar shnayim ayil echad shiva kvasim b'nei shana. One
ram. Okay so one ram tends to be the rule. So where
are you ever going to get אילים eilim in the plural in
any קרבן? korban?
So the גמרא Gemara actually has a place by שבועות. Shavuos. אי
דעצרת דתורת כהנים, Ee d'atzeret d'Toras Kohanim, how about where it speaks
about שבועות Shavuos in תורת כהנים Toras Kohanim in ויקרא? Vayikra? What
does it say there? That is in אמור. Emor. So what does
it say in אמור? Emor? It says the following. It says that
you know you bring this שתי הלחם, shtei halechem, ממושבתיכם תביאו לחם
תנופה שתים שתי עשרונים סלת תהיינה חמץ תאפינה בכורים לה׳. mimoshavoseichem tavi'u
lechem tnufa shtayim shtei esronim soles tiheyena chametz te'afena bikurim l'Hashem. And
then it says, והקרבתם על הלחם v'hikravtem al halechem specifically with the
שתי הלחם, shtei halechem, שבעת כבשים תמימים בני שנה ופר
בן בקר אחד ואילים שנים יהיו עולה לה׳ מנחתם ונסכיהם אשה לריח
ניחוח לה׳. shivas kvasim tmimim b'nei shana u'far ben vakar echad v'eilim
shnayim yihyu olah l'Hashem minchatam v'niskeihem isheh l'reiach nichoach l'Hashem. Now that
sounds like the מוסף Musaf that we read in במדבר, Bamidbar, but
is it the מוסף? Musaf? So let's say again, this is seven
כבשים, kvasim,
one cow, and two rams. The מוסף Musaf mentioned in שבועות Shavuos
in פינחס Pinchas is שבעה shiva is פרים בני
בקר שנים איל אחד שבעה כבשים. parim b'nei vakar shnayim ayil echad
shiva kvasim. It is
seven lambs, two cow, and one ram. Whereas here it is seven
lambs, one cow, and two rams. So the number of cow and
rams reverse themselves and the גמרא Gemara is going to say so
clearly this is a separate קרבן. korban. This is not the קרבן
מוסף. korban Musaf. This is specifically the קרבן korban associated with the
שתי הלחם. shtei halechem. And then it goes on and then we
of course have da-da-da-da-da,
you know, it says ועשיתם שעיר עזים אחד לחטאת ושני כבשים בני
שנה לזבח שלמים. va'asitem se'ir izim echad l'chatas u'shnei kvasim b'nei shana
l'zevach shlamim. There are also two sheep that are not an עולה,
olah, two sheep that are שלמים shlamim that are particularly considered to
go together with the שתי הלחם. shtei halechem. Okay we'll get back
to that. But now we're looking at this bigger קרבן, korban, this
עולה. olah. So here you have two rams. So that is the
two rams that the משנה Mishnah is referring to. So that explains
why the גמרא Gemara focused in on שבועות. Shavuos. It doesn't exactly
explain why it focused in on ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh more than
all the other חגים, chaggim, but anyway in the end that's what
the גמרא Gemara is landing on. שבועות Shavuos is the thing that
has multiple rams. But now we've got a problem. Okay or now
the גמרא Gemara will explain because the multiple cows are in במדבר,
Bamidbar, there it's two cows and one ram. And the multiple rams
are in אמור Emor in ויקרא, Vayikra, two rams and one cow.
But the משנה Mishnah says the sheep, the cows, and the rams.
So there's no one of those places that you have both all
those three things in the plural, sheep, cows, and rams. So let's
see what the גמרא Gemara says. לעולם דעצרת דתורת כהנים, L'olam d'atzeret
d'Toras Kohanim,
ואי דעצרת דתורת כהנים הויה כתיב בהו. v'ee d'atzeret d'Toras Kohanim havaya
ksiv behu. And if it is about what we have in ויקרא,
Vayikra, so there it says, I'm sorry I jumped a little ahead,
anyway there it says הויה. havaya. What does it say there? So
it says והקרבתם על הלחם שבעת כבשים תמימים בני שנה ופר בן
בקר אחד ואילים שנים יהיו עולה לה׳. v'hikravtem al halechem shivas kvasim
tmimim b'nei shana u'far ben vakar echad v'eilim shnayim yihyu olah l'Hashem.
Shall be. So the יהיו yihyu like before when it says כמשפטם
k'mishpatam means they're all required. So the גמרא Gemara says okay לעולם
דעצרת דתורת כהנים. l'olam d'atzeret d'Toras Kohanim. We are talking about the
rams in ויקרא. Vayikra. והכי קאמר. V'hachi ka'amar. Here's how you have
to read the משנה Mishnah and this is also addressing the problem
I mentioned that how do you have rams and plural rams and
plural cows all in the same place? לא אילים דתורת כהנים מעכבי
ליה לאיל דחומש הפקודים ולא איל דחומש הפקודים מעכבי להו לאילים דתורת
כהנים. Lo eilim d'Toras Kohanim me'akvei lei l'ayil d'Chumash HaPikudim v'lo ayil
d'Chumash HaPikudim me'akvei lehu l'eilim d'Toras Kohanim. When it says the rams
are not מעכב זה את זה, me'akev ze es ze, so actually
when you're dealing with the whole קרבן korban in ויקרא, Vayikra, the
whole seven sheep, two rams, one cow that comes with the שתי
הלחם, shtei halechem, all of those because it says יהיו, yihyu, all
of those are required and if you only have some you do
not bring them. They are מעכב זה את זה. me'akev ze es
ze. But when our משנה Mishnah says the אילים eilim are not
מעכב, me'akev, it means the אילים eilim of תורת כהנים Toras Kohanim
of the קרבן עולה korban olah that is brought with the שתי
הלחם shtei halechem does not, is not, if you don't have that
it does not prevent you from bringing the איל, ayil, the one
ram that comes with the מוסף Musaf in במדבר. Bamidbar. And similarly
if you don't have the מוסף Musaf of במדבר, Bamidbar, it doesn't
prevent you from the animals that come from the קרבן korban that
comes with the שתי הלחם. shtei halechem. So again, the גמרא Gemara
is trying to find one קרבן korban that has
פרים, parim, אילים, eilim, and
כבשים. kevasim. It can't deal with סוכות Sukkot because סוכות Sukkot it
says כמשפטן. kemishpatan. So the best it can do is you have
by שבועות Shavuos you have a plural אילים eilim by the קרבן
korban that comes with שתי הלחם shtei halechem and a plural of
פרים parim that comes with the קרבן korban of the מוסף. musaf.
So the אילים eilim are not מעכב זה את זה me'akev zeh
es zeh means the אילים eilim of ויקרא Vayikra are not מעכב
me'akev the אילים eilim of the שתי הלחם shtei halechem are not
מעכב me'akev the איל ayil of במדבר. Bamidbar. The איל ayil of
במדבר Bamidbar is not מעכב me'akev the אילים eilim of ויקרא. Vayikra.
But it actually all of the animals of ויקרא Vayikra for the
שתי הלחם shtei halechem are required. So now the גמרא Gemara says
okay, but that doesn't still work with the other words in the
משנה Mishnah about the פרים parim and the כבשים. kevasim. So the
גמרא Gemara says like this: ולא דקא מעכבי אהדדי אילים דתוספת קאמר.
v'lo de'ka me'akvi ahadadi eilim de'tosefes ka'amar.
אלא, Ela, so the גמרא Gemara says one minute, פרים דאפילו הדדי
לא מעכבי. parim de'afilu hadadi lo me'akvi. For one minute, when you
get to the cows and the sheep in our משנה, Mishnah, there
it's talking about the מוסף musaf and there it's saying that the
cows and the sheep not just say are not מעכב me'akev something
in ויקרא, Vayikra, it means even for the קרבן מוסף korban musaf
itself, if you don't have all the cows you still bring the
ones you can bring, if you don't have all the sheep you
bring the sheep you can bring. So when it's talking
about the מוסף, musaf, it means even within the מוסף musaf it's
not מעכב זה את זה. me'akev zeh es zeh. That's the פשט
pshat of the משנה. Mishnah. So that's what it's going to mean
when you're talking about the cows and the sheep that even within
the מוסף musaf it's not מעכב זה את זה. me'akev zeh es
zeh. But then when you get to the rams, לא במעכבי אילים
דהכא ודהכא הוא דלא מעכבי אינו מעכב. lo be'me'akvei eilim de'hacha u'dehacha
hu d'lo me'akvi inu me'akev. But when you're talking about the rams
it means something different. It means the rams of במדבר Bamidbar are
not, the rams of ויקרא Vayikra are not מעכב me'akev במדבר, Bamidbar,
במדבר Bamidbar is not מעכב me'akev ויקרא. Vayikra. But actually the rams
of ויקרא Vayikra are מעכב, me'akev, you need that whole sacrifice to
come together. So that's a bizarre read. By the cows and the
sheep it means even within the מוסף musaf you don't need all
the components, they're not מעכב, me'akev, and when it takes to the
rams you're talking about something completely different about its relationship to ויקרא.
Vayikra. That's completely bizarre. So the גמרא Gemara says yeah, תני מילי
מילי קתני, tani mili mili katani, the משנה Mishnah is talking about
different types of scenarios. Okay, when it's talking about the cows and
the sheep it's talking about within the מוסף, musaf, when it's talking
about the rams it's comparing the מוסף musaf for שבועות Shavuos to
the קרבן korban of the שתי הלחם shtei halechem for שבועות. Shavuos.
Anyway, this was a whole somersault the גמרא Gemara had to get
into because it decided that the rams literally meant the rams that
exist within a particular קרבן מוסף. korban musaf. Okay, but bottom line
the issue is that the גמרא Gemara seems to say that סוכות
Sukkot is an exception, by סוכות Sukkot all of them are needed
because of כמשפטן. kemishpatan. By שבועות, Shavuos, the קרבן korban that comes
with the שתי הלחם shtei halechem because it says יהיו, yihyu, all
of those are needed. But that is distinct from the מוסף musaf
of שבועות. Shavuos. And when it comes to all the other מוספין,
musafin, all the מוספין musafin except for
סוכות, Sukkot, there even if you only have one of the animals
you still bring it, there's nothing as מעכב זה את זה me'akev
zeh es zeh within a מוסף. musaf. Okay, now we are going
to interpret, learn out some of these הלכות halachos but also interpret
some difficult פסוקים pesukim in יחזקאל. Yechezkel. Okay, because when יחזקאל Yechezkel
gets to talking about כהנים kohanim and קרבנות korbanot he says a
lot of things that are not consistent with the תורה Torah as
the גמרא Gemara itself will see. So let's take a look at
the גמרא. Gemara. וביום החודש, U'veyom hachodesh, so this is in יחזקאל
מ"ו, Yechezkel mem vav, it's talking about the future בית המקדש Beis
Hamikdash and it's talking about ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh and here's what
the פסוק pasuk says. Let me find it.
Okay, so here it is, מ"ו ו'. mem vav vav. וביום החודש,
U'veyom hachodesh, on presumably ראש חודש, Rosh Chodesh, פר בן בקר תמימים,
par ben bakar temimim, one cow, וששת כבשים, ve'sheses kevasim, six sheep,
ואיל תמים יהיו, ve'ayil tamim yihyu, and one ram. The problem is
that the תורה Torah says two cows and seven sheep. So let's
see what the גמרא Gemara does with that. Okay, וביום החודש פר
בן בקר תמימים וששת כבשים ואיל תמימים יהיו. U'veyom hachodesh par ben
bakar temimim ve'sheses kevasim ve'ayil temimim yihyu. Okay, so פר מה תלמוד
לומר? par mah talmud lomar? What does it mean a cow?
לפי שנאמר בתורה פרים, Lefi she'ne'emar ba'Torah parim, because the תורה Torah
says the קרבן מוסף korban musaf is two cows. ומנין שאם לא
מצא שנים מביא אחד? U'minayin she'im lo matza shenayim mevi echad? How
do you know if you don't have two you can even bring
one? So here the לא מעכב זה את זה lo me'akev zeh
es zeh is literally even within the same
genre. If you don't have all the cows bring what you have.
ומנין שאם לא מצא מביא אחד תלמוד לומר פר. U'minayin she'im lo
matza mevi echad talmud lomar par. So that's why יחזקאל Yechezkel says
even if there's only one cow you bring it. Okay, ששת כבשים,
sheses kevasim, six sheep, מה תלמוד לומר? mah talmud lomar? Why does
it say that? לפי שכתוב בתורה, Lefi shekasuv ba'Torah, because the תורה
Torah says the קרבן מוסף korban musaf is שבעה, shiva, seven. ומנין
שאם לא מצא שבעה יביא ששה? U'minayin she'im lo matza shiva yavi
shisha? How do you know if you don't have seven bring six?
תלמוד לומר ששה. Talmud lomar shisha. says six to tell you you
don't need all the sheep, I mean if you bring what you
have.
ומניין שאם לא מצא ששה יביא חמישה, חמישה יביא ארבעה, ארבעה יביא
שלושה, שלושה יביא שניים, ואפילו אחד. u-minayin she-im lo matza shisha yavi
chamisha, chamisha yavi arbaah, arbaah yavi shlosha, shlosha yavi shnayim, ve-afilu echad.
Fine, how do you know though you can be missing more than
one? How do you know even if you have just one sheep
you can bring it? תלמוד לומר, talmud lomar, so the next פסוק
pasuk says, I'll read the next פסוק, pasuk, ואיפה לפר ואיפה לאיל
יעשה מנחה, מנחה, ve-eifa la-par ve-eifa la-ayil yaaseh mincha, mincha, so you
bring the appropriate מנחה, mincha, ולכבשים כאשר תשיג ידו ושמן הין לאיפה,
ve-lakvasim kaasher tasig yado ve-shemen hin la-eifa, and for the sheep what
you will are able to afford and you should bring a הין
hin of oil for the איפה eifa of flour. Now the problem
is that the also the proportions of the oil and the flour
are wrong, the גמרא's Gemara going to get to that, but when
it says for the sheep what you can afford, it sounds like
it's saying what you can afford for the מנחת נסכים, minchas nesachim,
for the flour and the oil and the wine, but the גמרא's
Gemara going to read it the sheep in terms of even the
number of sheep you bring, even if you could only afford one
you bring what you can bring. Okay, תלמוד
לומר ולכבשים כאשר תשיג ידו. talmud lomar ve-lakvasim kaasher tasig yado. ומאחר
דכתיב הכי, u-me-achar de-chtiv hachi, now what it was going to say
for the sheep whatever you can afford to mean even one, ששה
כבשים למה לי, shisha kvasim lama li, why did the earlier פסוק
pasuk say six sheep? דכמה דאפשר להדויי מהדרינן. de-khama de-efshar le-haduyei mahadrinan.
Okay, just because you can bring one if you only have one,
you try to bring as many as possible, and you don't say,
look, I'm not going to get all seven so who cares? If
once I'm not doing it the right way and I'm not getting
all seven I might as well just bring one. No, you bring
as many as you can. ומניין שמעכבין זה את זה? u-minayin she-me-akvin
ze et ze? Now this is a little strange, after just told
you you don't need all of them, it says how do you
know that they are מעכב meakev one another? תלמוד
לומר יהיו, ואייל תמים יהיו, talmud lomar yihyu, ve-ayil tamim yihyu, it
shall be. Okay, so what does that mean? What is מעכבין זה
את זה? me-akvin ze et ze? So if you look at רש"י,
Rashi, רש"י Rashi says אם יש להם פרים שנים או כבשים שבעה
שאין יכולים להקריב זה בלא זה, im yesh lahem parim shnayim o
kvasim shivah she-ein yecholim le-hakriv ze belo ze, that if you have
the full amount then you're not allowed to bring only some. What
does that mean? Means you're not יוצא yotzei if you had seven
sheep, if you only had six sheep and you brought them at
least you got part of the קרבן. korban. If you had seven
sheep and you only brought six, it's not a valid קרבן? korban?
It's not exactly clear what the מעכב meakev means in that context
because you have one, literally you're not יוצא yotzei because you have
the full complement? So if you take a look at תוספות, Tosfos,
he says מניין שמעכבין, minayin she-me-akvin, so first he quotes רש"י Rashi
and then he says אי נמי כמאן דאמר רבנן דפליגי עליה דרבי
שמעון בן ננס שהקריב פרים ולא יקריב נסכים מאחד מהם. i nami
k-man de-amar rabanan de-pligi alei de-Rabbi Shimon ben Nanas she-hikriv parim ve-lo
yakriv nesachim me-echad me-hem. So you know in the גמרא Gemara we
saw the position of רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon that better to bring
one cow with the נסכים nesachim rather than bringing all the cows
without. Implicitly the רבנן rabbanan disagreed but they never said it. So
תוספות Tosfos is saying maybe that's what מעכבין זה את זה me-akvin
ze et ze means. It doesn't literally mean מעכב, meakev, but it
means having all of the seven is a qualitatively different thing and
you have to work to ensure you have all of the seven
even if it means not having the נסכים. nesachim. Better to have
the unit of seven, that you get an A grade on it,
rather than having fewer with the נסכים, nesachim, the opposite of רבי
שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. Okay, so that's a nice read. אי נמי אם
יש לו כבשים ואין לו לתמיד בין הערביים מעכב כולהם לשם מוסף.
i nami im yesh lo kvasim ve-ein lo la-tamid bein ha-arbayim meakev
kulam leshem musaf. It says maybe it means if you have all
of the sheep but just the right amount, don't say oh I'm
going to save one sheep for the afternoon תמיד. tamid. No, better
to bring all the sheep and have the full מוסף, musaf, or
at least the full amount of sheep for the מוסף, musaf, even
if you don't bring, even it means not bringing the תמיד. tamid.
So again, מעכבין זה את זה me-akvin ze et ze doesn't mean
literally it stops you from being יוצא yotzei if you don't have
them all, but it means having all of them creates one unit
that is qualitatively different and that has to be given preference. Then
תוספות Tosfos asks is that really true that that would override the
תמיד tamid of the afternoon? Okay, so that's the מעכב meakev in
the sense that yes you can bring fewer than the full amount,
but the full amount does create its own unit. Now we're going
to look at, go to the previous פרק perek of יחזקאל, Yechezkel,
and once we're dealing with difficult פסוקים, psukim, deal with other difficult
פסוקים. psukim. Okay, so this is now in יחזקאל מה יח. Yechezkel
mem-hey yud-chet. כה אמר השם אלוקים בראשון באחד לחודש תקח פר בן
בקר תמים וחיטאת את המקדש. koh amar Hashem Elokim ba-rishon be-echad la-chodesh
tikach par ben bakar tamim ve-chiteita et ha-mikdash. So says the Lord
God on the first day on the first month, meaning ניסן, Nissan,
on the first of the month
you shall take a cow, an
ox, and you shall sanctify the מקדש. Mikdash. Okay, so the גמרא
Gemara says וחיטאת, ve-chiteita, חטאת? chatat? Over here? If you say you
sanctify, normally that's a word that you use with a קרבן חטאת
korban chatas is brought and then you sprinkle the blood as a
type of purification, but presumably by ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh we're talking
about the sacrifice of ראש חודש. Rosh Chodesh. So the sacrifice of
ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh has an ox or two oxen you know
for the עולה, olah, so why is it saying bring an ox
and then saying use it as as a חטאת. Chattat. So it
says אמר רבי יוחנן פרשה זו אליהו עתיד לדרשה. Amar Rabbi Yochanan
parsha zu Eliyahu atid l'darsha. I have no
idea, this is once again a difficult פסוק pasuk in יחזקאל, Yechezkel,
particularly around the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash and the כהנים. Kohanim. G-d
willing when אליהו הנביא Eliyahu Hanavi comes, he will explain to us
what this פסוק pasuk means. רב אשי אמר, Rav Ashi amar, now
רב אשי Rav Ashi says you don't need to wait for אליהו,
Eliyahu, I've got פשט. pshat. מילואים הקריבו בימי עזרא כדרך שהקריבו בימי
משה. Miluim hikrivu bimei Ezra k'derech shehikrivu bimei Moshe. This was sort
of prophesying the second בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, and יחזקאל Yechezkel was
after the חורבן churban of the first בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. And
this was saying when they sanctify the second בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash,
they will go through a sanctification purification
initiation process, a מילואים miluim process, like they did with the משכן
Mishkan in the time of משה. Moshe. And there they also used
an ox, an ox, עגל, egel, whatever, but they used the blood
and they used it to do a
purification, חיטוי, chittuy, and also the eighth day of the מילואים miluim
was on ראש חודש ניסן, Rosh Chodesh Nissan, so it does work
out that
way. תוספות Tosafos says it's not exactly parallel, there are a lot
of differences, but at least it's a version of the מילואים miluim
and the sanctification they will do, which will happen on ראש חודש
ניסן. Rosh Chodesh Nissan. תניא נמי הכי, Tanya nami hachi, we taught
similarly. רבי יהודה אומר פרשה זו אליהו עתיד לדרשה. Rabbi Yehuda omer
parsha zu Eliyahu atid l'darsha. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda already said before
רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, I don't know what it means, אליהו Eliyahu
will explain it. אמר לו רבי יוסי, Amar lo Rabbi Yose, רבי
יוסי Rabbi Yose said, מילואים הקריבו בימי עזרא, miluim hikrivu bimei Ezra,
no, this is prophesying that they will bring מילואים miluim or like
initiation sacrifices at the time of עזרא Ezra כדרך שהקריבו בימי משה,
k'derech shehikrivu bimei Moshe, like they did בימי משה. bimei Moshe. אמר
לו, Amar lo, so רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda said to רבי יוסי,
Rabbi Yose, תנוח דעתך שהנחת את דעתי. tanuach datcha shehinachta es daati.
Your mind should be at peace because you made my mind at
peace. When you say אליהו Eliyahu will explain it, it means I
don't have a good answer, so I was stuck with a problem,
and you now helped me make sense of it. Thank you so
much. Okay, now another difficult פסוק pasuk in יחזקאל, Yechezkel, we're going
back, that was פרק מ"ה, perek mem-hey, now we're in פרק מ"ד.
perek mem-daled. What does it say in פרק מ"ד? perek mem-daled? וכל
נבילה וטריפה מן העוף ומן הבהמה לא יאכלו הכהנים.
V'chol neveila u'treifa min ha'of u'min habeheima lo
yochlu hakohanim. Any נבילה, neveila, any animal
that dies without being properly slaughtered is how it's understood or טריפה,
treifa, an animal that has been attacked is probably the literal meaning,
but of course the way חז"ל Chazal understand it was properly slaughtered
but it had an injury that it was going to die. So
whether it is of the birds or of the larger animals, the
כהנים kohanim should not eat it. So of course the גמרא Gemara
says, כהנים הוא דלא יאכלו הא ישראל אכלו? kohanim hu d'lo yochlu
ha'Yisrael achlu? כהנים kohanim can't eat it but a normal ישראל Yisrael
can eat it? That doesn't make any sense. So אמר רבי יוחנן
פרשה זו אליהו עתיד לדרשה. amar Rabbi Yochanan parsha zu Eliyahu atid
l'darsha. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan goes back to stand by, I have
no idea what it's talking about, G-d willing אליהו Eliyahu will explain
it when אליהו הנביא Eliyahu Hanavi comes. רבינא אמר, Ravina amar, רבינא
Ravina says, כהנים איצטריכא ליה. kohanim itzrichlei. No, no, the point is
even כהנים kohanim cannot eat this. Why? Why might I have thought
that כהנים kohanim get a dispensation? סלקא דעתך אמינא, salka daatach amina,
I might have thought, הואיל ואישתרי מליקה לגבייהו, ho'il v'itishrei melika gabei'u,
since כהנים kohanim they do מליקה melika by the bird sacrifices and
they cut its neck from behind and that would in all other
cases when it wasn't a bird sacrifice that would make it a
נבילה. neveila. תשתרי נמי נבילה וטריפה? tishrei nami neveila u'treifa? So maybe
that's just giving the כהנים kohanim a general license to eat נבילה
neveila and טריפה? treifa? קא משמע לן, kamashma lan, so it's teaching
you not that way, that even though that's permitted in the מקדש
mikdash by bird sacrifice, it is not permitted elsewhere. It's actually nice
within that because it says
מן העוף ומן הבהמה. min ha'of u'min habeheima. Normally נבילה neveila and
טריפה treifa they apply to birds but we normally associate them more
with בהמה, beheima, so that's a nice read because עוף of is
allowed in the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, nevertheless it is not allowed
outside the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. Okay, another פסוק pasuk back to
פרק מ"ה perek mem-hey in
יחזקאל. Yechezkel. וכן תעשה בשבעה בחודש מאיש שוגה ומפתי וכיפרתם את הבית.
V'chein taaseh b'shivah bachodesh m'ish shogeh u'mipesi v'chipertem es habayis. After it
speaks about what you are going to do
on
ראש חודש, Rosh Chodesh, specifically after it says what you're going to
do on ראש חודש ניסן, Rosh Chodesh Nissan, which we identified as
a type of purification initiation of the המקדש, Hamikdash, then the next
פסוק pasuk says so shall you do on the seventh of the
month, the seventh of ניסן, Nissan,
from a man who is in error and is foolish or errs,
וכיפרתם את הבית, v'chipertem es habayis, and you shall purify the house.
So what the heck is this talking about? שבעה, shiva, what does
this mean seven? So here finally רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan is able
to explain it. אמר רבי יוחנן אלו שבעה שבטים שחטאו. Amar Rabbi
Yochanan eilu shiva shevatim shechat'u. We're not talking about the seventh of
the month, we're talking about the cow, the ox, that is brought
when the בית דין Beis Din פוסק'ס paskins incorrectly and most of
בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael follow their rulings, and then that's the בית
דין Beis Din brings a special קרבן, korban, פר העלם דבר של
ציבור, par helem davar shel tzibur, it is the topic of the
entire... entire מסכת הוריות, Masechet Horayos, okay, and he says that is
what we are talking about, not the seventh of the month. But
so what does seven mean? If seven of the tribes sin, the
majority of seven of the tribes, even though or all of the
seven of the tribes, even if it doesn't constitute the majority in
numbers of like it's, you know, it's like they have what is
it called, you know, the,
you know, it's sort of like they get the electoral vote and
not the popular vote, okay? So you have seven tribes but they
don't constitute a majority of the people, nevertheless, that constitutes all of
Israel followed the ruling. Okay, so אמר רבי יוחנן Amar Rabbi Yochanan
אלו שבעה שבטים שחטאו Eilu shiva shevatim shechatu seven of the tribes
sinned ואף על פי שאין רובא דקהלא ve'af al pi she'ein ruba
dekahala even if it's not the majority of the entire nation. חודש
Chodesh so what does it mean בשבעה בחודש beshiva bachodesh
seventh of the month? No, חודש Chodesh means אם חידשו ואמרו חלב
מותר im chidshu ve'amru cheilev mutar that the בית דין Beis Din
innovated and they incorrectly ruled that some thing that you're deserving of
כרת kares for like eating חלב cheilev forbidden fat was permissible. וכן
תעשה vechein ta'aseh similarly shall you do that you shall bring an
ox, this special פר העלם דבר של ציבור Par He'elam Davar Shel
Tzibbur בשבעה beshiva if seven of the tribes sinned בחודש bachodesh which
is בחידוש bechidush because of a innovated incorrect ruling of the בית
דין. Beis Din. Okay, and now keep on reading מאיש שוגג me'ish
shogeg
אם חידשו ואמרו חלב מותר im chidshu ve'amru cheilev mutar מאיש שוגג
me'ish shogeg an erring person ומיפתי umipeti מלמד שאין חייבים אלא על
העלם דבר עם שגגת מעשה. melamed she'ein chayavim ela al he'elam davar
im shigegat ma'aseh. It's not enough that they were מחדש mechadesh they
innovated and ruled incorrectly, it has to be איש שוגג ish shogeg
that people erred as a result and followed their ruling. So a
very brilliant way of reading the פסוק pasuk of resolving a difficult
פסוק pasuk and of establishing some basic הלכות halachos about פר העלם
דבר של ציבור. Par He'elam Davar Shel Tzibbur. Okay. אמר רב יהודה
אמר רב Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Rav so said רב יהודה Rav
Yehuda in the name of רב, Rav, I'm sorry, מלמד שאין חייבים
אלא על העלם דבר עם שגגת מעשה melamed she'ein chayavim ela al
he'elam davar im shigegat ma'aseh which teaches you that they are only
obligated with a incorrect ruling and then a error in the following
people followed that ruling. אמר רב יהודה אמר רב Amar Rav Yehuda
Amar Rav זכור אותו האיש לטוב zachor oto ha'ish letov the following
man should be remembered for good וחנינא בן חזקיה שמו v'Chanina ben
Chizkiya shemo his name is חנינא בן חזקיה Chanina ben Chizkiya שאלמלא
הוא נגנז ספר יחזקאל she'ilmala hu nignaz sefer Yechezkel if it wasn't
for him the book of יחזקאל Yechezkel would have been, you know,
put away. It would have been like buried. We would not have
included it in the canon. Why? שהיו דבריו סותרים דברי תורה shehayu
devarav sotrim divrei Torah because on the face of it a lot
of things contradict what the תורה Torah says as we've just been
talking. The קרבנות korbanos are not the same. It seems like certain
things are אסור assur only to the כהנים, Kohanim, other things about
the כהנים Kohanim don't match up what it says in the תורה.
Torah. So מה עשה meh asah so what did this man do?
העלה שלש מאות גרבי שמן he'ela shalosh me'os garvei shemen he brought
up three hundred flasks of oil, you know, to keep the lights
burning וישב בעליה ודרשם veyashav ba'aliya vedarsham and he, you know, sat
up in his attic and he explicated them, he found ways, he,
you know, did an all-nighter, maybe he brought other rabbis there together
with him and they found ways to interpret the verses like we
just did so they are not contradictory to the תורה Torah which
allowed יחזקאל Yechezkel to be kept within the canon. Okay, last part
now of the משנה. mishnah. אמר רבי שמעון Amar Rabbi Shimon אם
היו להם פרים מרובים im hayu lahem parim merubim it's רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon says better to bring one ox with its with its
נסכים nesachim rather than all the oxen and we saw before that
תוספות Tosafos claimed that the חכמים Chachamim would disagree that actually all
of the oxen together is a higher קיום, kiyum, you know, as
a unit of seven or whatever the unit is than one ox
with its נסכים. nesachim. תנו רבנן Tanu Rabbanan and guess what, רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon is going to get this from a פסוק pasuk
by יחזקאל. Yechezkel. ואיפה לפר ואיפה לאיל Ve'eifa lapar ve'eifa la'ayil and
an איפה eifa for the ox and an איפה eifa for the
ram יעשה מנחה ya'aseh mincha you should do for the מנחה mincha
ולכבשים כאשר תשיג ידו velakevashim ka'asher tasig yado and for the sheep
as your as you will, you know, be able to afford. So
that was we read that before. ושמן הין לאיפה veshemen hin la'eifa
and a שמן shemen oil a הין hin worth per איפה. eifa.
אמר רבי שמעון Amar Rabbi Shimon וכי מדת פרים ואילים אחת היא
vechi middat parim ve'eilim achas hi is this this says an איפה
eifa for both the cow and the ram? But they don't have
the same amount of flour. Not only that, the amount that they
have is not an איפה. eifa. So the amount is wrong also,
but איפה eifa could just mean measure. But he's saying but they
don't have the same measure. אלא Ela what this is telling you
is שאם היו להם פרים מרובים ולא היו נסכים she'im hayu lahem
parim merubim velo hayu nesachim or נסכיו nesachav נסכים nesachim יביאו
פר אחד ונסכיו ואיל אחד ונסכיו ויקריבו כולם בלא נסכים. yaviu par
echad venesachav ve'ayil echad venesachav veyakrivu kulam belo nesachim. So this is
what רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says that איפה לפר eifa lapar is
telling you the measure with the ox ואיפה לאיל ve'eifa la'ayil and
the measure with the ram, those are a unit and those have
to go together and you should preference having let's say the ox
and its measure
over over having let's say the ox and the ram without its
measure. The ox with its measure, the ram with its measure. ואם
היו להם אילים ve'im hayu lahem eilim and if they had rams
מרובים merubim or money not actually the rams, if they had the
money for a lot of rams ולא היו להם איפתם velo hayu
lahem eifasam but not enough for their
their flour. flower and oil, יביאו איל אחד ואיפתו yaviyu ayil echad
ve'efato you bring one of them with the flour and oil and
oil with the מנחת נסכים minchas nesachim rather than bringing all of
the animals. That at least is רבי שמעון's Rabbi Shimon position. We
do not have an explicit חכמים chachamim that disagree, but it is
quite possible the חכמים chachamim disagree. Let's see the next משנה. mishnah.
הפר
והאילים והכבשים והשעיר אין מעכבין את הלחם. ha-par ve'ha'eilim ve'ha'kevasim ve'ha'se'ir ein
me'akvin es ha-lechem. So thankfully because we just mentioned שבועות, Shavuos, we
are continuing with that discussion. So we mentioned that there's a whole
קרבן korban of an עולה, olah, which is made up of
seven פרים parim and two rams and one sheep and and that,
you know, that comes with the שתי הלחם. shetei ha-lechem. And it
says here that that is not מעכב. me'akev. Okay.
Excuse me, I think I said that wrong. Seven sheep, seven sheep,
two rams and one ox. Okay. Right.
So actually the plural is correct here. הפר ha-par the one ox,
האילים ha-eilim the two rams, והכבשים ve'ha'kevasim and the seven sheep. Okay.
So those are not מעכב. me'akev.
Excuse me, השעיר ha-se'ir and the שעיר se'ir which is the חטאת,
chatat, אין מעכבין את הלחם. ein me'akvin es ha-lechem. So we said
earlier in the גמרא gemara that they're all מעכב me'akev one another.
Certainly the עולה olah part is all מעכב me'akev one another. You
need the whole עולה olah and if you don't have that whole
עולה, olah, all of those animals, then it's not good. Okay. But
if you do not have any of those animals, אין מעכבין את
הלחם, ein me'akvin es ha-lechem, you can still go ahead and bring
the שתי הלחם. shetei ha-lechem. ולא הלחם מעכבן velo ha-lechem me'akvan and
if you don't have the שתי הלחם, shetei ha-lechem, you can still
go ahead and bring all of these animals. Each one can come
separately. Okay. הלחם מעכב את הכבשים. ha-lechem me'akev es ha-kevasim. Now that's
in terms of that because that's an
עולה olah that is brought with the bread, but is not, you
know, intimately tied and bound to the bread. The thing that is
bound to the bread is the two lambs of the שלמים, shelamim,
right? Because then it says like this, ועשיתם שעיר עזים אחד לחטאת
ושני כבשים בני שנה לזבח שלמים והניף הכהן אותם על לחם הבכורים
תנופה לפני ה' על שני כבשים קדש יהיו לה' לכהן va'asitem se'ir
izim echad le'chatat u'shenei kevasim benei shanah le'zevach shelamim ve'hinif ha-kohen otam
al lechem ha-bikkurim tenufah lifnei Hashem al shenei kevasim kodesh yihyu la-Hashem
la-kohen and he should wave them with the bread. And then it
says specifically the them does not mean the lambs and the חטאת,
chatat, but just the lambs, על שני כבשים. al shenei kevasim. So
the כבשים, kevasim, the two lambs of the שלמים shelamim are waved
together with the two loaves of bread. That is one tight unit.
And there the question is going to be is one מעכב me'akev
the other? So the עולה olah that comes, the special עולה olah
for the שתי הלחם shetei ha-lechem is not מעכב me'akev the שתי
הלחם shetei ha-lechem and vice versa. But what about the שלמים shelamim
that are waved with the שתי הלחם? shetei ha-lechem? What's that story?
Okay. So הלחם מעכב את הכבשים ואין הכבשים מעכבין את הלחם, ha-lechem
me'akev es ha-kevasim ve'ein ha-kevasim me'akvin es ha-lechem, דברי רבי עקיבא. divrei
Rabbi Akiva. So רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says if you don't have
the bread, okay, don't bring the lambs. The only purpose of the
lambs is for the sake of the
bread. Okay. ואין הכבשים מעכבין את הלחם ve'ein ha-kevasim me'akvin es ha-lechem
and more than that, if you don't have the lambs, you can
still bring the bread. The bread is primary and the bread can
be brought by itself. With the bread, you bring the lambs. Okay.
But if you don't have the bread, don't bother with the lambs.
But if you only have the bread, that's fine also. אמר בן
ננס, amar Ben Nanos, לא כי. lo ki. No, that's not the
way it is. אלא הכבשים מעכבין את הלחם והלחם אינו מעכב את
הכבשים. ela ha-kevasim me'akvin es ha-lechem ve'ha-lechem eino me'akev es ha-kevasim. It's
the reverse. Okay. If you do not have the lambs, then don't
bring the bread. Okay. And that is because, you know, the bread
is coming on the lambs. So you need to start with the
lambs. If you don't have the lambs, you can't bring the bread.
Okay. והלחם אינו מעכב את הכבשים. ve'ha-lechem eino me'akev es ha-kevasim. If
you have the lambs, they can operate without the bread. So it
is the lambs that are necessary, not the bread that is necessary.
Now what's his proof? And that is the way we rule. שכן
מצינו כשהיו ישראל במדבר ארבעים שנה קרבו כבשים בלא לחם. sheken matzinu
keshehayu Yisrael ba-midbar arba'im shanah kirevu kevasim belo lechem. So when בני
ישראל Bnei Yisrael were in the wilderness for the forty years, okay,
they brought the קרבנות korbanos that are mentioned in אמור, Emor, right?
They're right there in ויקרא. Vayikra. They were given at the beginning
of the forty years, but they didn't have the bread because the
whole idea of the שתי הלחם shetei ha-lechem is only, you know,
it says when you come to the land. So there was no
bread that was being brought, no שתי הלחם, shetei ha-lechem, but they
brought the rest. They brought the lambs. How does he know that?
I don't know, but okay. You know, presumably it tells you, it
told them these מצוות, mitzvos, so they did everything except the thing
they couldn't do. They didn't do the bread. אף כאן יקריבו כבשים
בלא לחם. af kan yakrivu kevasim belo lechem. Here too you can
do the lambs without the bread. And therefore the lambs are the
foundation. אמר רבי שמעון, amar Rabbi Shimon, הלכה כדברי בן ננס, halachah
kedivrei Ben Nanos, we rule like בן ננס, Ben Nanos, אבל אין
הטעם כדבריו, aval ein ha-ta'am kidevarav, but not for the reason he
given. Why? שכל האמור בחומש הפקודים קרב במדבר shekol ha-amur be-Chumash ha-Pekudim
karev ba-midbar because anything that's in במדבר, Ba-midbar, which is your standard
מוסף, musaf, that they brought in במדבר. Ba-midbar. וכל האמור בתורת כהנים
vekol ha-amur be-Toras Kohanim but what's said in ויקרא Vayikra and אמור,
Emor, particularly in the context, probably not כל האמור, kol ha-amur, but
particularly in the context of שבועות, Shavuos, לא קרב. lo karev. But
not for the reason he gives. Why? שכל האמור בחומש הפקודים קרב
במדבר shekol ha'amur b'chumash hapikudim karav bamidbar because anything that's in במדבר
Bamidbar which is your standard מוסף Musaf that they brought in במדבר.
Bamidbar. וכל האמור בתורת כהנים v'chol ha'amur b'Torat Kohanim but what's said
in ויקרא Vayikra and אמור Emor particularly in the context, probably not
כל האמור, kol ha'amur, but particularly in the context of שבועות, Shavuot,
אין קרב במדבר ein karav bamidbar was not offered up in the
מדבר. midbar. How do you know? It's well we'll see in the
גמרא Gemara but basically if all of those things, that whole big
עולה, olah, the special two lambs of the שלמים, shlamim, if all
of those were connected to the bread and you didn't bring the
bread, none of that started until they got into ארץ ישראל. Eretz
Yisrael. So that's number one. No, you're wrong. I'm not they didn't
bring those things yet until they got into ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael.
Okay. אין קרב במדבר. ein karav bamidbar. וכל האמור בתורת כהנים ומשבאו
לארץ קרבו אלו ואלו. v'chol ha'amur b'Torat Kohanim umishebao la'aretz karvu eleh
v'eleh. When they got to ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael then it all
kicked in. Okay, well if that's true though, then why do you
rule, then why are you saying the הלכה halacha is like what
he said? Maybe without the bread you don't bring anything. That's what
happened in the מדבר. midbar. So ואלו ומפני מה אני אומר יקרבו
כבשים בלא לחם? v'eleh umipnei mah ani omer yikrvu kvasim belo lechem?
So then why do I say the lambs come without the bread
but not the reverse? מפני שהכבשים מתירים את עצמם ולא הלחם מתיר
את עצמן mipnei shehakvasim matirim et atzmam v'lo halechem matir et atzman
because
it gets to the question of you cannot have anything as a
קרבן korban without a מתיר. matir. You don't just bring something, right?
You gotta sprinkle the blood on the מזבח, mizbeach, burn the קטורת,
ketoret, burn the burn the קומץ. komets. There has to be a
מתיר. matir. So if the bread is sanctified, what is going to
make it from a sanctified קרבן korban that nobody can benefit from
to something that can now be consumed and eaten? There's nothing from
the bread that goes on the מזבח. mizbeach. The only thing you're
going to do is שחט shacht the קרבן, korban, שחט shacht the
כבשים kvasim and sprinkle their blood on the מזבח. mizbeach. So the
כבשים kvasim without the bread, they have a מתיר. matir. The blood
is the מתיר. matir. It's just a normal קרבן. korban. You can
go ahead and eat it. Okay? You don't so so that can
be brought independent of the bread. Okay? ולא הלחם בלא כבשים, v'lo
halechem belo kvasim, but you can't bring the bread without the lambs,
שאין לו מתירין she'ein lo matirim because there's there's nothing that that
makes the bread edible now, that turns it from a קרבן korban
into something that can now be consumed because something of it went
on the מזבח. mizbeach. The only thing that goes on the מזבח
mizbeach is the blood of the lambs. So when you wave it
together it's like one unit, and now you שחט shacht the lambs
and you put the blood on the מזבח, mizbeach, that is a
מתיר matir for the bread. So you can have the lambs without
the bread because they have a מתיר, matir, you can't have the
bread without the lambs because they don't have a מתיר. matir. So
I'm not interested in the conceptual question of which is the עיקר
ikar and which is the טפל. tafel. Which is you might be
right fundamentally it's all for the sake of the bread. And that's
why it didn't wasn't practiced until they came into ארץ ישראל Eretz
Yisrael until it was a time when they were ready to bring
the bread. Okay, that's conceptually. But once it kicks in, even if
the purpose is for the bread, when it comes down to it,
you can bring the lambs function by themselves and the bread does
not function by itself. Let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara.
תנו רבנן. Tanu rabanan. והקרבתם על הלחם חובה. v'hikravtem al halechem chova.
So we תניא, tanya, a בריתא, braita, you shall bring on the
bread, right? And this is talking about the whole big the two
excuse me, the one ox, the seven sheep, the two rams, that
whole big עולה olah that's brought with the bread. So that's an
obligation. והקרבתם על הלחם חובה עליכם. v'hikravtem al halechem chova aleichem. שבעת
כבשים תמימים, shiv'at kvasim tmimim, seven
seven lambs, אף על פי שאין לחם. af al pi she'ein lechem.
So והקרבתם על הלחם v'hikravtem al halechem sounds like this big עולה's
olah gonna be like the two lambs, like the שלמים, shlamim, and
it's gonna be totally connected to the bread and that you need
without one you don't have the other. But then it goes on
and it says שבעת כבשים תמימים, shiv'at kvasim tmimim, and somehow they
learn from that because that means that the שבעת כבשים תמימים shiv'at
kvasim tmimim exist by itself. The whole עולה olah exists without the
bread. So what is it? Is this whole עולה olah deeply connected
to the bread or can it exist independently? So אם כן מה
תלמוד לומר על הלחם? im ken mah talmud lomar al halechem? So
if it means that it's not מעכב me'akev and you could bring
the עולה olah without the bread and the bread without the עולה
olah like we said in the משנה, Mishnah, אם כן מה תלמוד
לומר על הלחם? im ken mah talmud lomar al halechem? So what
is the purpose of connecting it to the bread? מלמד שלא נתחייבו
בכבשים קודם שנתחייבו בלחם דברי רבי טרפון. melamed shelo nitchayvu bikvasim kodem
shenitchayvu belechem divrei Rabbi Tarfon.
So this is to tell you that this קרבן korban did not
kick in until they got to ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. Okay so
yes, it is connected to the bread. This is even going about
the עולה. olah. And this is like the גמרא Gemara said like
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon also said in the משנה, Mishnah, which is
that none of this they're connected in the conceptual sense that none
of this קרבן, korban, whether it's the שני כבשים shnei kvasim that
are the שלמים shlamim that are waved with the bread, whether it
is this whole big עולה olah about the ox and the rams
and the sheep, none of that applied until they got into ארץ
ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. That's why it says על הלחם al halechem 'cause
all of this is because of the שתי הלחם. shtei halechem. So
it all kicks in when you get into ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael.
But in practice that doesn't mean they're מעכב זה את זה. me'akev
zeh et zeh. The עולה olah is not מעכב me'akev the... And
vice versa. Okay, that's what רבי טרפון *Rabbi Tarfon* says. רבי עקיבא
אומר יכול הן הן כבשים האמורים כאן הן הן כבשים האמורים בחומש
פקודים *Rabbi Akiva omer yakhol hen hen kevasim ha'amurim kan hen hen
kevasim ha'amurim bechumash pikudim*. So רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* now taking he's
first making a different point. Perhaps the seven sheep that are mentioned
here, the seven sheep that are mentioned in במדבר *Bamidbar* for the
מוסף *Musaf*, is this which it says bring with the bread the
same as the מוסף *Musaf* in that it says in פינחס *Pinchas*.
So we've already discussed this. אמרת *Amarta*, he says, well maybe you
would think it because it's both seven sheep in both places and
it's all an עולה *Ola*, but כשתגיע אצל פרים ואילים אינם הם
*kesheta-magi’a etzel parim ve'eilim einam heim*. But the ox and the rams
and the ox is different. In במדבר *Bamidbar* it is two oxen
and one ram, and in ויקרא *Vayikra* אמור *Emor* it is one
ox and two rams. אלא הללו באין בגלל עצמן והללו באין בגלל
לחם *Ella halalu ba’in biglal atzman vehalalu ba’in biglal lechem*. So the
stuff in במדבר *Bamidbar* in פינחס *Pinchas* is a מוסף *Musaf* completely
independent like all the מוספים *Musafim* in פינחס *Pinchas*, and the stuff
happening here in אמור *Emor*, that is a special קרבן עולה *Korban
Ola* brought together with the bread, completely distinct from the מוסף *Musaf*
mentioned in פינחס *Pinchas*. נמצא מה שאמר בחומש פקודים קרב במדבר מה
שאמר בתורת כהנים לא קרב במדבר *Nimtza ma she’amar bechumash pikudim karav
bamidbar ma she’amar betorat kohanim lo karav bamidbar*. And this is similar
building on רבי טרפון *Rabbi Tarfon*, and I buy into what רבי
טרפון *Rabbi Tarfon* just said. So the מוסף *Musaf* which has nothing
to do with the bread, that was offered in the wilderness, but
the big עולה *Ola* mentioned in אמור *Emor*, which is connected to
the bread, it says על הלחם *al halechem* to tell you that
its time does not begin until they enter ארץ ישראל *Eretz Yisrael*.
But again, just because the time does not begin until they enter
ארץ ישראל *Eretz Yisrael* doesn't mean that when it actually comes to
bring it, that it is מעכב *me'akev*, because it is not. The
עולה *Ola* is not מעכב *me'akev* the bread and vice versa. ודילמא
פרים ואילים לאו אינהו הכבשים אינהו נינהו *Vidi’ilma parim ve'eilim lav inhu
hakvasim inhu ninhu*. So the גמרא *Gemara* says one minute, okay, you
proved to me that the ox and the ram in פינחס *Pinchas*
is different than the ox and the ram in אמור *Emor* because
the numbers are different, but both of them have seven sheep, so
maybe at least the seven sheep is the same and it's referring
at least there they're overlapping and it is referring to the seven
sheep of the מוסף *Musaf*. So the גמרא *Gemara* says no, מדהני
אישתנו הני נמי דאחריני *midehani ishtanu hani nami dachrinei*. No, since the
ram and the ox are different, clearly the sheep is also different.
Clearly we're talking about a fundamentally different קרבן *Korban*. One is a
מוסף *Musaf* and the other is the קרבן *Korban* brought with the
bread. ופרים ואילים ממאי דאישתנו *Ufarim ve'eilim mimai de’ishtanu*? Who tells you
just because it's two and one in one place and one and
two in the other that it's really a different קרבן *Korban*? דילמא
הכי קאמר רחמנא אי בעי פר ושני אילים ליקרב אי בעי שני
פרים ואיל אחד ליקרב *Dilma hachi kamar rachamana ibei par ushnei eilim
leikarev ibei shenei parim ve’ayil echad leikarev*. Maybe they're both talking about
the מוסף *Musaf*, and in one place it says two ox and
one ram, and the other place it says one ox and two
rams, to tell you you have a choice, you can do it
either way, either seven one and two or seven two and one,
maybe that's what it's saying, but fundamentally it's מוסף *Musaf*. So the
גמרא *Gemara* says no, מדאישתני סדרן שמע מינה אחריני נינהו *mide’ishtani sidran
shema mina achrinei ninhu*. Because the order is also different. Why? Because
in אמור *Emor* it is, where are we, it is שבעת כבשים
תמימים ופר בן בקר ואילים שנים *shiv’at kvasim tmimim upar ben bakar
ve’eilim shnayim*, seven sheep, one ox, two rams. And in פינחס *Pinchas*
it is פרים בני בקר שנים *parim bnei bakar shnayim*, it starts
with the ox, two oxen, one ram, seven sheep. So clearly the
תורה *Torah* is going out of its way to signal that these
are fundamentally different קרבנות *Korbanot*. What you get in פינחס *Pinchas* is
the list of מוספים *Musafim* and what you get in אמור *Emor*
is specifically connected to the מצוה *Mitzvah* of the יום *Yom* and
of the שתי הלחם *shtei halechem*. So the whole קרבן *Korban* there
is a different קרבן *Korban*, it's very similar but it's a different
קרבן *Korban*, it is seven sheep,
one ox, two rams, that's coming because of the שתי הלחם *shtei
halechem* in the sense that according to most positions here it did
not kick in until they entered into ארץ ישראל *Eretz Yisrael*. But
in the actual bringing, not מעכב זה את זה *me'akev zeh et
zeh*. You can bring the עולה *Ola* without the שתי הלחם *shtei
halechem*, the שתי הלחם *shtei halechem* without the עולה *Ola*. And tomorrow
we'll get to the second part of the משנה *Mishna* which is
the מעכבין זה את זה *me’akvin zeh et zeh* or which way
it's מעכב *me’akev* when it comes to the two lambs of the
שלמים *shlamim* that are coming with the שתי הלחם *shtei halechem*. Okay,
we will end here.